In this video we'll talk about
在这段视频中 我们要讲
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
an approach to building a
一种构建推荐系统的方法
recommender system that's called collaborative filtering.
叫做协同过滤(collaborative filtering)
The algorithm that we're talking
我们所讲的算法
about has a very interesting
有一个值得一提的
property that it does
特点 那就是它能实现
what is called feature learning and
对特征的学习
by that I mean that this
我的意思是
will be an algorithm that can
这种算法能够
start to learn for itself what features to use.
自行学习所要使用的特征
Here was the data set that
我们建一个数据集
we had and we had
假定是为每一部电影准备的
assumed that for each movie,
对每一部电影
someone had come and told
我们找一些人来
us how romantic that
告诉我们这部电影
movie was and how much action there was in that movie.
浪漫指数是多少 动作指数是多少
But as you can imagine it
但想一下就知道
can be very difficult and time
这样做难度很大
consuming and expensive to actually try
也很花费时间
to get someone to, you know,
你想想 要让每个人
watch each movie and tell
看完每一部电影
you how romantic each movie and
告诉你你每一部电影有多浪漫 多动作
how action packed is each
这是一件不容易的事情
movie, and often you'll
而且通常
want even more features than just these two.
你还会希望得到除这两个特征之外的其他指数
So where do you get these features from?
那么你怎样才能得到这些特征呢？
So let's change the problem
所以 让我们转移一下问题
a bit and suppose that
假如我们
we have a data set where
有某一个数据集
we do not know the values of these features.
我们并不知道特征的值是多少
So we're given the data set
所以比如我们得到一些
of movies and of
关于电影的数据
how the users rated them, but we
不同用户对电影的评分
have no idea how romantic each
我们并不知道每部电影
movie is and we have no
到底有多少浪漫的成分
idea how action packed each
也不知道到底每部电影里面动作成分是多少
movie is so I've replaced all of these things with question marks.
于是我把所有的问题都打上问号
But now let's make a slightly different assumption.
现在我们稍稍改变一下这个假设
Let's say we've gone to each of our users, and each of our users has told has told us
假设我们采访了每一位用户 而且每一位用户都告诉我们
how much they like the
他们是否喜欢
romantic movies and how much
爱情电影 以及
they like action packed movies.
他们是否喜欢动作电影
So Alice has associated a current of theta 1.
这样 Alice 就有了对应的参数 θ(1)
Bob theta 2.
Bob 的是 θ(2)
Carol theta 3.
Carol 的是 θ(3)
Dave theta 4.
Dave 的是 θ(4)
And let's say we also use this
我们还有这样的假设
and that Alice tells us
假如 Alice 告诉我们
that she really
她十分喜欢
likes romantic movies and so
爱情电影
there's a five there which
于是 Alice 的特征 x1
is the multiplier associated with X1 and lets
对应的值就是5
say that Alice tells us she
假设 Alice 告诉我们
really doesn't like action movies and so there's a 0 there.
她非常不喜欢动作电影 于是这一个特征就是0
And Bob tells us something similar
Bob 也有相似的喜好
so we have theta 2 over here.
所以也就有了 θ(2) 的数据
Whereas Carol tells us that
但 Carol 说
she really likes action movies
她非常喜欢动作电影
which is why there's a 5 there,
于是这个特征就被记录为5
that's the multiplier associated with X2,
也就是 x2 的值
and remember there's also
别忘了
X0 equals 1 and let's
我们仍然有等于1的 x0
say that Carol tells us
假设 Carol 告诉我们
she doesn't like romantic
她不喜欢爱情电影之类的
movies and so on, similarly for Dave.
而且戴夫也是这样
So let's assume that somehow
于是 我们假定 某种程度上
we can go to users and
我们就可以着眼于用户
each user J just tells
看看任意的用户 j
us what is the value
对应的 θ(j) 是怎样的
of theta J for them.
这样就明确地告诉了我们
And so basically specifies to us of how much they like different types of movies.
他们对不同题材电影的喜欢程度
If we can get these parameters
如果我们能够从用户那里
theta from our users then it
得到这些 θ 参考值
turns out that it becomes possible to
那么我们理论上就能
try to infer what are the
推测出每部电影的
values of x1 and x2 for each movie.
x1 以及 x2 的值
Let's look at an example.
举例来说
Let's look at movie 1.
假如我们看电影1
So that movie 1 has associated
于是电影1就对应于
with it a feature vector x1.
表示特征的向量 x1 联系在一起了
And you know this movie is called Love at last but let's ignore that.
这部电影的名字叫《爱到最后》 但这不重要
Let's pretend we don't know what
假设我们不知道
this movie is about, so let's ignore the title of this movie.
这部电影的主要内容 所以也不要在意电影的名字
All we know is that Alice loved this move.
我们知道的就是 Alice 喜欢这部电影
Bob loved this movie.
Bob 喜欢这部电影
Carol and Dave hated this movie.
Carol 和 Dave 不喜欢它
So what can we infer?
那么我们能推断出什么呢？
Well, we know from the
好的 我们从
feature vectors that Alice
特征向量知道了
and Bob love romantic movies
Alice 和 Bob 喜欢爱情电影
because they told us that there's a 5 here.
因为他们都在这里评了5分
Whereas Carol and Dave,
然而 Carol 和 Dave
we know that they hate
我们知道他们不喜欢
romantic movies and that
爱情电影
they love action movies. So
但喜欢动作电影
because those are the parameter
由于你知道这些
vectors that you know, uses 3 and 4, Carol and Dave, gave us.
是可以从 第3和第4个参数看出来的
And so based on the fact
同时 由于我们知道
that movie 1 is loved
Alice 和 Bob
by Alice and Bob and
喜欢电影1
hated by Carol and Dave, we might
而 Carol 和 Dave 不喜欢它
reasonably conclude that this is probably a romantic movie,
我们可以推断 这可能是一部爱情片
it is probably not much of an action movie.
而不太可能是动作片
this example is a little
这个例子在数学上
bit mathematically simplified but what
可能某种程度上简化了
we're really asking is what
但我们真正需要的是
feature vector should X1 be
特征向量 x(1) 应该是什么
so that theta 1 transpose
才能让 θ(1) 的转置
x1 is approximately equal to 5,
乘以x(1) 约等于5
that's Alice's rating, and
也就是 Alice 的评分值
theta 2 transpose x1 is
然后 θ(2) 的转置乘以 x(1)
also approximately equal to 5,
也近似于5
and theta 3 transpose x1 is
而 θ(3) 的转置 乘以 x(1)
approximately equal to 0,
约等于0
so this would be Carol's rating, and
这是 Carol 的评分
theta 4 transpose X1
而 θ(4) 的转置乘以 x(1)
is approximately equal to 0.
也约等于0
And from this it looks
由此可知
like, you know, X1 equals
x(1) 应该用
one that's the intercept term, and
[1 1.0 0.0] 这个向量表示
then 1.0, 0.0, that makes sense
第一个1 是截距项
given what we know of Alice,
这样才能得出
Bob, Carol, and Dave's preferences
Alice Bob Carol 和 Dave 四个人
for movies and the way they rated this movie.
对电影评分的结果
And so more generally, we can
由此及之 我们可以
go down this list and try
继续列举 试着
to figure out what might
弄明白
be reasonable features for these other movies as well.
其他电影的合理特征
Let's formalize this problem of learning the features XI.
让我们将这一学习问题标准化到任意特征 x(i)
Let's say that our
假设我们的用户
users have given us their preferences.
告诉了我们的偏好
So let's say that our users have
就是说用户们
come and, you know, told us
已经给我们提供了
these values for theta 1
θ(1) 到 θ(nu) 的值
through theta of NU
and we want to learn the
而我们想知道
feature vector XI for movie
电影 i 的
number I. What we can
特征向量 x(i) 我们能做的
do is therefore pose the following optimization problem.
是列出以下的最优化的问题
So we want to sum over
所以 我们想要把
all the indices J for
所有指数 j 相加
which we have a rating
得到对电影 i 的评分
for movie I because
因为我们
we're trying to learn the features
想要求得电影 i 的特征
for movie I that is this feature vector XI.
也就是向量 x(i)
So and then what we
所以现在我们
want to do is minimize this squared
要做的是最小化这个平方误差
error, so we want to choose
我们要选择
features XI, so that,
特征 x(i)
you know, the predictive value of
使得 我们预测的用户 j
how user J rates movie
对该电影 i 评分的预测值评分值
I will be similar,
跟我们从用户 j 处
will be not too far in the
实际得到的评分值
squared error sense of the actual
不会相差太远
value YIJ that we actually observe in
也就是这个差值
the rating of user j
不要太大
on movie I. So, just to
所以 总结一下
summarize what this term does
这一阶段要做的
is it tries to choose features
就是为所有
XI so that for
为电影评分的
all the users J that
用户 j
have rated that movie, the
选择特征 x(i)
algorithm also predicts a
这一算法同样也预测出一个值
value for how that user would have rated that movie
表示该用户将会如何评价某部电影
that is not too far, in
而这个预测值
the squared error sense, from the
在平方误差的形式中
actual value that the user had rated that movie.
与用户对该电影评分的实际值尽量接近
So that's the squared error term.
这就是那个平方误差项了
As usual, we can
和之前一样
also add this sort of
我们可以加上一个正则化项
regularization term to prevent
来防止特征的数值
the features from becoming too big.
变得过大
So this is how we
这就是我们
would learn the features
如何从一部特定的电影中
for one specific movie but
学习到特征的方法
what we want to do is
但我们要做的是
learn all the features for all
学习出所有电影的
the movies and so what
所有特征
I'm going to do is add this
所以我现在要做的是
extra summation here so
在此加上另外的一个求和
I'm going to sum over all Nm
我要对所有的电影 nm 求和
movies, N subscript m movies, and minimize
n 下标 m 个电影
this objective on top
然后最小化整个这个目标函数
that sums of all movies.
针对所有的电影
And if you do that, you end up with the following optimization problem.
这样你就会得到如下的最优化的问题
And if you minimize
如果你将这个最小化
this, you have hopefully a
就应该能得到所有电影的
reasonable set of features for all of your movies.
一系列合理的特征
So putting everything together, what
好的 把我们
we, the algorithm we talked
前一个视频讨论的算法
about in the previous video and
以及我们刚刚
the algorithm that we just talked about in this video.
在这个视频中讲过的算法合在一起
In the previous video, what we
上一个视频中
showed was that you know,
我们讲的是
if you have a set of
如果你有一系列
movie ratings, so if you
对电影的评分 那么如果你
have the data the rij's and
有r(i,j) 和 y(i,j)
then you have the yij's that will be the movie ratings.
也就是对电影的评分
Then given features for your
于是 根据不同电影的特征
different movies we can learn these parameters theta.
我们可以得到参数 θ
So if you knew the features,
这样 如果你知道了特征
you can learn the parameters
你就能学习出不同用户的
theta for your different users.
参数 θ 值
And what we showed earlier in
我们之前
this video is that if
这个视频中讲的是
your users are willing to
如果用户愿意
give you parameters, then you
为你提供参数 那么你就
can estimate features for the different movies.
可以为不同的电影估计特征
So this is kind of a chicken and egg problem.
这有点像鸡和蛋的问题
Which comes first?
到底先有鸡还是先有蛋？
You know, do we want if we can get the thetas, we can know the Xs.
就是说 如果我们能知道 θ 就能学习到 x
If we have the Xs, we can learn the thetas.
如果我们知道 x 也会学出 θ 来
And what you can
而这样一来 你能做的
do is, and then
就是
this actually works, what you
如果这真的可行的话
can do is in fact randomly
实际上你能做的就是
guess some value of the thetas.
随机猜de θ 的值
Now based on your initial random
基于你一开始随机
guess for the thetas, you can
猜测出的 θ 的值
then go ahead and use
继你可以继续下去
the procedure that we just talked
运用我们刚刚讲到的
about in order to
步骤 我们可以学习出
learn features for your different movies.
不同电影的特征
Now given some initial set
给出已有的一些电影的
of features for your movies you
原始特征
can then use this first
你可以运用
method that we talked about
我们在上一个视频中讨论过的
in the previous video to try to get
第一种方法 可以得到
an even better estimate for your parameters theta.
对参数 θ 的更好估计
Now that you have a better setting of the parameters theta for your users,
这样就会为用户提供更好的参数 θ 集
we can use that to maybe
我们就可以用这些
even get a better set of
得到更好的
features and so on.
特征集或者其他数据
We can sort of keep
然后我们可以继续
iterating, going back and forth
迭代 不停重复
and optimizing theta, x theta,
优化θ x θ
x theta, nd this
x θ 这非常有效
actually works and if you
如果你
do this, this will actually
这样做的话
cause your album to converge
你的算法将会收敛到
to a reasonable set of
一组合理的电影的特征
features for you movies and a
以及一组对合理的
reasonable set of parameters for your different users.
对不同用户参数的估计
So this is a basic collaborative filtering algorithm.
这就是基本的协同过滤算法
This isn't actually the final
这实际并不是最后
algorithm that we're going to use. In the next
我们将要使用的算法
video we are going to be able to improve
下一个视频中
on this algorithm and make
我们将改进这个算法
it quite a bit more computationally efficient.
让其在计算时更为高效
But, hopefully this gives you
但是这节课希望能让你
a sense of how you
基本了解如何
can formulate a
构建一个问题
problem where you can simultaneously
在这个问题中
learn the parameters and simultaneously learn the features from the different movies.
从不同的电影处学到参数以及特征
And for this problem, for the
对于这个问题
recommender system problem, this is
对于推荐系统
possible only because each user
可能就根据每个用户
rates multiple movies and hopefully
对多部电影的评分
each movie is rated
以及每部电影由
by multiple users. And so
由不同用户的评分
you can do this back and
这样你就可以反复进行这样的过程
forth process to estimate theta
来估计出 θ 和 x
and x.  So to
总结一下
summarize, in this video we've
在这个视频中
seen an initial collaborative filtering algorithm.
我们了解了最基本的协同过滤算法
The term collaborative filtering refers
协同过滤算法指的是
to the observation that when
当你执行这个算法时
you run this algorithm with a
你通过一大堆用户
large set of users, what all
得到的数据
of these users are effectively doing are sort of
这些用户实际上在高效地
collaboratively--or collaborating to
进行了协同合作
get better movie ratings for
来得到每个人
everyone because with every
对电影的评分值
user rating some subset with the movies,
只要用户对某几部电影进行评分
every user is helping the
每个用户就都在帮助算法
algorithm a little bit to learn better features,
更好的学习出特征
and then by helping--
这样 通过自己
by rating a few movies myself, I will be helping
对几部电影评分之后
the system learn better features and
我就能帮助系统更好的学习到特征
then these features can be used
这些特征可以
by the system to make better
被系统运用 为其他人
movie predictions for everyone else.
做出更准确的电影预测
And so there is a sense of
协同的另一层意思
collaboration where every user is
是说每位用户
helping the system learn better features
都在为了大家的利益
for the common good. This
学习出更好的特征
is this collaborative filtering.
这就是协同过滤
And, in the next video what we
在下一个视频中
going to do is take the ideas that
我们要把这些想法
have worked out, and try to
付诸实施
develop a better an even
尝试开发一种
better algorithm, a slightly better
更完美的算法
technique for collaborative filtering.
为协同过滤算法做出一点改进